This is DeepSeek V4 Flash, a 284-billion-parameter Mixture-of-Experts model.
The GGUF file used here is about 150 gigabytes on Hugging Face.
The machine is a 64 gigabyte M1 Max.
So the question is not just whether the machine can compute the model.
It is whether the operating system can bring the right expert weights into memory at the right time.
Dense models tend to reuse the same mapped weight ranges during decode.
DeepSeek V4 Flash is different.
It routes each token through a changing subset of experts, so decode can become dominated by page-in latency.
The benchmark model is lovedheart slash DeepSeek-V4-Flash-GGUF, using the MXFP4_MOE GGUF file.
The model file itself is not included in GitHub. The repository includes scripts, patches, charts, and reproduction notes.
For the video, I show live token generation so viewers can see the local model actually producing text.
The optimization is intentionally small. The model stays mmap-backed, and CPU repacking is disabled.
After the MoE router chooses the active experts, the runtime calls MADV_WILLNEED on those expert matrix ranges.
The operating system still owns the file-backed cache, so pages remain reclaimable.
The clean decode comparison uses the same model, the same prompts, and no static prewarm in either case.
With the expert page hint disabled, decode generation averaged 0.98 tokens per second.
With routing-aware MADV_WILLNEED enabled, it averaged 1.23 tokens per second.
That is a 25.4 percent throughput gain without changing the model.
The long-run data also showed that prefill and decode should be optimized differently.
Prefill behaves like broad layer-level page-in throughput. Decode is more latency-sensitive.
That is why a single global cache policy is probably not enough for this kind of model.
The repository includes parser artifacts, benchmark data, charts, and a rebuild process for the packed expert export.
This is not a claim that a 64 gigabyte machine is the ideal way to run a model this large.
It is a demonstration that for sparse MoE models, local inference is often about memory residency and page-in timing, not just raw compute.
MoE-MADV means Mixture-of-Experts plus MADV_WILLNEED.
The project is available at github.com slash daystar7777 slash MoE-MADV.