This is a 150 gigabyte DeepSeek V4 Flash MoE model.
It is running locally on a 64 gigabyte M1 Max.
The system specs, memory pressure, GPU history, and elapsed time are on screen.
Now the model is actually generating tokens from the local GGUF file.
This part is fast-forwarded because generation is slow on a model larger than RAM.
For this MoE model, the hard part is bringing the right expert pages into memory at the right time.
MoE-MADV gives macOS a MADV_WILLNEED hint after routing chooses the active experts.
On the decode benchmark, generation improved from 0.98 to 1.23 tokens per second.
That is a 25.4 percent throughput gain without changing the model.
The scripts, data, and charts are on GitHub at daystar7777 slash MoE-MADV.